# GABRIEL MADIGAN, PhD

🗣 USA 💃 +1 (408) 457-4671 🔀 gabemadigan@gmail.com 🛮 in gabrielmadigan 🕡 gmadigan 🚱 gmadigan.github.io

#### **EXECUTIVE SUMMARY**

I have 10 years of experience as a data scientist, where I have helped international scientific collaborations analyze terabytes of data and publish results in peer-reviewed journals. I have led a search for new physics at the highest-energy particle accelerator in the world by developing Python-based data processing frameworks, building and training ML models, and applying statistical methods that resulted in a peer-reviewed journal publication I co-authored. My current projects involving ML technologies include natural language processing and computer vision.

#### **EDUCATION**

Northeastern University

Boston, MA

PhD, MSc, Department of Physics

Sept 2016 - May 2023

Doctoral thesis: A search for leptoquarks decaying to muons and bottom quarks

University of Massachusetts Amherst

Amherst, MA

BSc, Department of Physics

Sept 2013 - May 2016

## TECHNICAL SKILLS

Languages - Python, SQL, C++, Git

Tools - PyTorch, Keras, Scikit-learn, Pandas, NumPy, SciPy, Matplotlib, Jupyter Notebooks, SpaCy, Gensim, ROOT Machine Learning - Deep learning (NN, RNN, LSTM, CNN), classification, regression, decision trees, gradient boosting Mathematics - Probability and statistics, partial differential equations, linear algebra

### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

Research Physicist CMS Collaboration

Sept 2016 – July 2023

Geneva, Switzerland

- Searched for new fundamental physics alongside 4000 scientists from over 50 countries by analyzing terabytes of recordbreaking high-energy particle collisions at CERN's Large Hadron Collider
- Co-authored a research paper constraining searches for a theorized elementary particle by placing the most stringent lower bound to date on the particle's mass at a 95% confidence level
- o Enhanced the sensitivity of an analysis to new physics by 10% after training machine learning models on terabytes of noisy particle collision data
- o Presented research at international conferences and participated in feedback cycles as both a reviewer and author of collaboration papers seeking publication

**Teaching Assistant** 

Sept 2016 – May 2018

Northeastern University College of Science

Boston, MA

 Led 40 undergraduates through weekly four-hour-long experimental physics labs covering physics theory, experimental techniques, and statistical analysis

NSF Undergraduate Research Fellow (REU)

May 2015 - August 2015

Telescope Array

Salt Lake City, UT

- o Contributed research into the origins and composition of ultra-high-energy cosmic rays by characterizing atmospheric conditions used in a publication, resulting in an uncertainty estimate of 8.5% on cosmic ray energy measurements
- o Operated the Telescope Array detectors for data acquisition of cosmic ray showers and identified damaged detectors on a three-person team during a 24-hour on-site shift

## Undergraduate Research Assistant

ATLAS Collaboration

Jan 2014 - May 2016

Amherst, MA

- Searched for new fundamental physics alongside 6000 scientists from over 40 countries by analyzing terabytes of recordbreaking high-energy particle collisions at CERN's Large Hadron Collider
- Tested exotic theories predicting extra spatial dimensions by placing lower bounds on the energy scale of these phenomena and developed an analysis framework in C++ to process recorded collision data